<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Fotis Koutoulakis]]></title>
  <link href="http://NlightNFotis.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://NlightNFotis.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-14T12:50:18+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://NlightNFotis.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Fotis Koutoulakis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="http://NlightNFotis.github.io/blog/2013/07/14/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-14T12:24:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://NlightNFotis.github.io/blog/2013/07/14/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>A new beginning</h1>

<p>Oh boy! A new start. Isn&rsquo;t that exciting? You bet it is. It&rsquo;s not however
my first introduction to blogging. I used to have a <a href="http://lambdareflection.wordpress.com">blog</a>
on Wordpress.com, but after a while I was turned off by the fact that it felt too limited.
So I decided I wanted a new place for me to host my online presence, that wasn&rsquo;t so much limited as Wordpress was.
Initially I was thinking about renting a VPS and self hosting wordpress there. But after doing a little research,
I came across <a href="http://pages.github.com">Github Pages</a>. I started investigating
Github pages some more, and found <a href="http://jekyllrb.com">jekyll</a> to be very <strong>very</strong> interesting.
After a while, I also came across <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>. That was it. I was sold :)</p>

<p>Free hosting of a blog, no need to maintain a server, and a platform written in <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org">ruby</a>?</p>

<p>Without hesitation, I immediately started working on it. I went through octopress documentation, (which needless to say, but it was fantastic)
found a wonderful theme online at <a href="http://opthemes.com">opthemes</a>, (kudos to <a href="http://alexgaribay.com">Alex Garibay</a> for that)
and got started.</p>

<p>And here we are. On a platform that you can hack and customize to your liking &ndash; at least more so than the locked down version of wordpress.
On a platform that is written on a language that I don&rsquo;t hate with passion (like cough, <strong>php</strong>, cough),
and may actually learn in the future, just for the sake of being able to customize every bit of it (gotta love the hacker&rsquo;s way)
&ndash; even though I am not really interested in web development per se.</p>

<p>Hope it starts out nice. I guess that is left to be seen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
